you um the format is about 20 to 30 minutes and we
will have some time for discussion later after the
after the talk and it's an informal environment
so if you need to go please go and i hope to see
you in the time for catch up later after the the
talk itself so for today's seminar i'm really
excited to have here jenny wong from university
of grenoble presenting us dynamo simulation with
established stratified f layer at the base
of earth's outer core thank you jenny okay
uh i will share my stream
great so is everything okay yes it is thank you
okay thank you for the nice introduction anita
um so yeah um i'm jenny i'm a post-doctoral
researcher at easter in grenoble and so as amita
said i'll be talking about dynamo simulations with
a stably stratified flare at the base of earth's
outer core and this work was mostly done um at
my postdoc at ipg paris uh in conjunction with uh
julian ober so um this is uh just a nice picture
of our wonderful earth our beautiful planet
and if i took a giant sized knife and cut it in
half and take you on a journey into the earth's
deep interior you'll see these distinct
layers so at the surface we have the crust
and then beneath that we have the rocky silicon
mantle um alloyed with uh like oh sorry uh a
rocky silicate mantle and then we have the uh
liquid outer core uh oh no sorry my slides just
skipped sorry then we have the liquid article
which is um made of a metallic uh ion uh
alloyed with light elements and it's
liquid it's vigorously convecting
um and it's enclosing the central uh solid
inner core sorry my keyboard input's not working
why can't i click okay and then we have the
uh inner core here sorry for the technical
problems just said um so so we have um so
yeah we have this um convecting um metallic uh
liquid outer cot and this is mostly driven by
heat left over from the formation of the planet
so this is known as secular cooling which
is uh the main uh thermal energy source for
thermal convection in the liquid book however
because we have a uh metallic alloy which is
allowed with um light elements uh we have
some uh solidification of the inner core
which releases some latent heat into um into the
system to drive convection and we also know that
the light elements preferentially partition
into the liquid as well so this gives us also
a chemical source of buoyancy in order to drive
convection in this liquid region so we have all
this vigorous um convection occurring and this
leads to a reference date in the liquid article
which is really well mixed and homogeneous and
its temperature profile is close to adiabatic
so all of this convection drives a process
called the geodynamo which generates a magnetic
field and protects us from solar winds and is
responsible for lovely things like the northern
lights and in terms of its spatial structure its
field is uh mainly dipole like barbecue and over
time we know that this field has persisted um
for um about four billion years through analyzing
singles aircon crystals so this time scale is uh
very long and vast and it's much longer than the
time scale that we know for the magnetic field to
dissipate away naturally which is estimated to be
on the order of 10 000 years so this discrepancy
in the time scales supports the idea that the
field is being continually regenerated and
sustained by this process called a geodynamo
so the question i'd like to
focus on today inside the core
is this region called the so-called uh
efflair at the base of the liquid article
so this is a seismically slow region which is um
first which was first observed by syrian pupille
back in 1991 and this is a puzzling and anomalous
layer because compared with what we might would
we might expect from a model such as prem which
assumes that we have a adiabatic core throughout
this seismically slow observation in comparison
with that infers a stably stratified layer at
the bottom of the arthritic core that can't be
explained by adiabatic compression alone so um
the goal of my ph oh sorry the goal of my phd was
actually to explain the dynamics of maintaining
such an f layer against convection using a slurry
iron snow model but what i'd like to focus on more
today is actually looking at how the presence of
the f-ware can impact core dynamics in general in
the bulk of the core so in order to probe this um
there is a sort of a well-established mathematical
framework for investigating this so um first
of all um we have the navier-stokes equation
so we're assuming we have an incompressible fluid
and um this is the navier-stokes equation with um
inertia on the left-hand side here we have the
pressure gradient this is the coriolis force
uh this is the viscous force the lorentz force
and finally a thermochemical buoyancy so it's
not like your classic thermal buoyancy that
you might find in really been our convection
this is um c parameter or this c um field is
actually a combination of thermal and chemical
variations uh this prime donates the
fluctuations away from the reference state
uh and this field itself is um so this code entity
field is also given by its own transport equation
uh so this is the equation of state for this code
entity field so this kind of explicitly says that
it's composed of thermal and um chemical
uh fluctuations and the transport equation
is here so it describes how the code density
field can change over time due to infection
and um diffusion as well we also
have a sink source term because we're
continually partitioning light elements
into the liquid bulk so in order to conserve
this quantity we introduce a numerical sink in
order to yeah to pull this law of conservation
and then finally we have a magnetic induction
equation so this means that we have no magnetic
monopoles and this is um basically describing
how the magnetic field changes over time due to
the electromotive force so there's a feedback
between the fluid flow and the magnetic field
which is incorporated into this force and this
includes things like advection of magnetic field
and magnetic stretching by the flow and this is
the diffusion term so this system of equations
that i've just presented are in a dimensionless
form so you can see these there's these uh
dimensionless control parameters um in this
presentation and um they're defined as follows
so here we have a flux based rayleigh number
so compared to the classical rayleigh number
um this takes into account um buoyancy driven by
thermochemical sources which is denoted by this f
value here which is the code entity flux and
this is a ratio between that flux and rotation
in the system here is the ecma number which is the
ratio between the viscous forces and the coriolis
force this is the prandtl number which is the
viscous over um the diffusivity of the co-density
and this is the magnetic pencil number
uh which is the ratio between viscous and
the magnetic diffusivity um so this is kind
of the sort of the frame the framework that
we use to probe card dynamics that's used very
commonly in dynamo calculations and in order to
solve those equations we need to impose some
boundary conditions as well so the velocity
is subject to uh stress-free conditions at the
unicorn boundary and at the cornman's boundary
and then also we have a coupled system in
which the inner core is free to rotate so
it's electrically conducting in its
rigid body that can super rotate
subject to electromagnetic and gravitational
talks with the rest of the system and we also have
assume electrically insulating mental because we
have a silica rocky medium there and we implement
this coupling between the core and the mantle
because it's able to reproduce well-known features
of a magnetic field that we can observe at the
surface of the earth known as secular variation
so one such feature is the observed westward
drift of the magnetic field uh seen from uh
you know ground observatories
and satellite observations
so onto sort of the more novel bit this is how
the f layer is invoked through imposing boundary
conditions on the code entity so we have um
we impose a gradient on we we impose a sorry
a condition on the gradient of the variations in
the code entity field at the inner core boundary
uh given by this value here and this introduces
a parameter uh called f i and this is
in this instance which is the ratio between
the total uh code density flux at the inner
core boundary and the total code
density flux at the aflare radius
and this essentially control controls
the strength of stratification
um within the f layer and you can um sort
of relate this to something more well known
such as the buoyancy frequency or the visalus
frequency uh through this relationship here
and so this is the boundary condition at
the f layer radius uh given by so and since
we are assuming that we have a purely adiabatic
heat flux at the cmb we say that the variations
in the co-density gradient at
this boundary is equal to zero
so in order to solve these equations and perform
dynamic simulations we're using a code called
parity which was originally uh written by emanuel
domi and further developed by julian ober and this
uses spherical harmonic extensions in the
theta in five directions uh with the second
order finite difference method in the radial
direction and we have an increase uh sorry a
decrease in the spacing uh in between the radial
grid points towards the boundaries in order to
try and capture more small scale effects
there and we time step through the code um
using a current nicholson scheme for the diffusion
terms and adding specifics for the other terms
and uh we fixed the dimensions
in those parameters as follows
so uh for the flux based rayleigh number we have
2.7 times 10 to the minus 5. and on the right hand
side of this column is what we would expect um in
the earth's regime and for the eckman number we
choose uh 3 times 10 to the minus 5 for the earth
it's 10 to the minus 15. so again we have this uh
big discrepancy between what we fix in this model
and what we might expect in the earth and this is
because we are really limited by the computational
power needed and in order to resolve uh resolve um
sort of uh small scale features if we went
to the earth's ratio however in the dynamo
community there's been a lot of effort to
develop robust scaling analyses in order to
allow extrapolation to the earth's regime um
so even though we choose these conservative
values it um still is indicative of what
we might expect in the real earth um and
also we fixed the prandtl number one uh for
anything much less than that the magnetic field is
not so much dipole dominated anymore which is um
not representative of what we know about the earth
and this is the magnetic parental number we
choose and um it should be noted that the
ecma number and the parental magnetic principal
number should be decreased together because at
some point there's not enough energy to maintain
the magnetic field against aromatic dissipation
um so that they're kind of you have to
decrease them both together for the f
layer radius um we choose a dimensionless radius
of 0.7 which corresponds to about 350 kilometers
in dimensional units from size mixed studies uh
we actually see in the literature that the f layer
thickness can be anywhere between
150 and maybe up to 400 kilometers
and then finally we have the uh buoyancy frequency
um to control the strength of stratification
within the earth layer so in this model um we've
implemented 14.7 um and then there's not really
any estimates in the literature for the earth but
just using a really crude estimate um from prem in
the airflow it might be expected to be around 13.
so here are some uh 3d uh videos of the um phi
velocity on the left hand side the radial magnetic
field in the middle and the co-density field
on the right hand side so from the blue color
you can see immediately that there's very strong
retrograde flows everywhere due to this uh coupled
uh coupled model uh between the core and the
mantle and we have this super rotating inner core
and given by the red colors here and the dynamics
of the flow are quite distinctive inside the
this region compared to the outside and this
imaginary region is called the tangent cylinder
so this is a basically an imaginary volume that
is um just touching the inner core boundary that
extends in the z direction but you could imagine
that with an f layer the effective tangent
cylinder region would be increased due
to um uh the presence of a stable region
at the bottom of the earth's outer core um so
within the tangent cylinder region we have more
plume-like and large upwellings occurring whereas
outside the tangent cylinder we have columnar
structures due to the influence of rotation um
in the magnetic field there are intense regions
that break up the klemner structure of the flow
and the scale of the magnetic field um we have
some large scale structures in the bulk and more
smaller scale folk features and at the f layer
radius which is also reflected in the small-scale
plumes that you can see in the code entity field
um and this is through the buoyancy
generated from the latent heat and
light element release here which results in
bottom driven and convection you can also see
that light elements tend to pile up within the
tangent cylinder given by the yellow area here
so i'm just looking at some time average fields
and spatially average fields this is a meridional
section uh through the core with uh no f layer so
on the left hand side again we see the velocity
uh in the middle it's the magnetic field and
on the right hand side it's cure density and
the colours denote the fire direction and
the line contours and the other meridional
components so from a fluid dynamical perspective
what i've done is um sort of artificially
increased the radius of the inner core to
the um a flare radius that i'm comparing to
because this makes sure that um i'm
comparing the same convective volume
between the two so that there's a similar um
overall buoyancy uh power in order and yeah
so uh this reference case again yeah
has an artificially inflated inner core
uh you can see that um immediately you a first
order observation would be that the amplitude of
the uh zonal velocity is much stronger with an f
flare at the equator beneath the cmb compared with
the reference case um and this is mainly because
the convective shear in the system and that's
being partitioned um between the local share at
the cmb and the share close to the icb so what
sorry what's essentially happening is that f layer
of reducing the shear between the liquid and solid
um at the icb which therefore contributes to the
remote electromagnetic magnetic torques and also
enhances the westwood flow beneath cmb in order to
conserve the total angular momentum of the system
we also can see from the meridional contours that
are dwellings in the tangent cylinder diverge
under the cmb and converge towards the tangent
cylinder edge in this twisting polar vortex
which produ produces a local minimum in the
magnetic field at the poles since the field
lines are infected away with a diverging flow
under the core surface and amplified here at the
tangent cylinder edge due to field line stretching
um so this uh describes uh the dynamics that um
it results in these polar magnetic minima and
actually between the two cases the magnetic
energy content is 1.3 times stronger with a flare
uh just from looking at the alsacer number and
um as i said light elements pilot within
the tangent cylinder and here we have weaker
lateral gradients in the co density field and
we believe this alters the thermal wind balance
which is the balance between coriolis uh coriolis
forces uh buoyancy and the lorentz force so this
uh this results in the rearrangement of
the um five velocity in which you can see
um so yeah we have you can see the relationship
between how the changes in the co-density field
can influence the um call flow structures through
this thermal wind balance and then looking at more
of an observational perspective rather than
a fluid dynamical one it'd be interesting
to see how the magnetic field morphology
the core surface um can be compared um
to the observations that we might see from
satellite data so in our simulations um here
for our reference case we have a regular
size in a core with no airflare and on
the left-hand side we have the full resolution
and on the right-hand side we've truncated the
radial magnetic field here that we're seeing
at the core surface to degree 13 which is
consistent with what we might see from
the observations um and with the efflair
we have images like so and you can see that the
colour barrel range uh tells us that we have uh
more surface field uh exiting the shell here in
the f layer case than than without and um you can
also see uh yeah we have a stronger surface
field about the same elsa number because of
um more field exiting the shell and also
in these pictures you can see these patches
of weaker field which are the polar magnetic
minima that i mentioned in the previous
slide and you can see this sharp gradient that
is coincident with the tangent cylinder radius
and so be interesting to know whether
this signature could be observed
from the observations and maybe perhaps like it's
it's it's kind you could probably hypothesize that
tangent cylinder radius has has an influence
on the envelope of the polar magnetic minima um
in this case the latitude is uh shifted by about
10 degrees uh with a a flare radius of 0.7 so
in varying the f layer radius um i've taken
a range of radii like so and here are the
corresponding dimensional values and what i've
looked at is a phi averaged and time averaged um
radial field at the cost surface as a function
of latitude so this is the reference case again
which corresponds to what we saw on the previous
slide and and here is the the peak at which you
see the envelope of the polar magnetic minimum so
there's one here and one here for for both poles
and uh the reference case at this peak is
coincident uh with the tangent cylinder radius
at 69 degrees and with the increasing layer
thicknesses you can see how this peak shifts
as a function of the flare radius so that this
location um increases by about two degrees uh
for every 100 kilometers in uh and it'll be
really interesting to make a comparison to
current geomagnetic models such as
gfm chaos and cover-ups in order to
see if we can detect such a signature and provide
some kind of independent constraint on the eflair
radius in addition to what we can
see in seismology so uh in summary um
we've looked at um how a stably stratified
f layer might affect core dynamics
and what we see is um strong westward azimuthal
flows that are particularly enhanced close to
the cmv and acquainter due to the re arrangement
of thermal winds and this is caused by the lack
of local shear between the inner core and the
effluent um this then through angular momentum
conservation changes the local shear at the cmb
which means that more field can exit the future
and uh would it be possible to see a signature
of f of the f layer in geomagnetic observations
well i've tried to probe this by changing the f
way of thickness and see its effect on um well
which effectively changes the tangent cylinder
radius and then therefore trying to see if there's
a corresponding change in the latitude of the
polar magnetic minimum so um i think i'd like to
wrap up here and thank you for your attention
and i'd be happy to answer any questions
thank you jenny great presentation
let's give a big round of applause
and it is time now for questions
if everybody in the audience
has one uh you can unmute yourself andy you're
ready hi hi andy hi anita hi jenny um thanks for
really great talk some very very interesting stuff
there um so a question and um first of all then is
uh how long did you run these models for how many
magnetic diffusion times or what fraction of a
magnetic fusion time yeah um so in these models
it's at least two um so i've not had time to run
them for much longer because obviously you know
they take a long time uh but yeah there's been a
lot of checks to see whether uh the especially
with the rotation involved whether things have
equilibrated so making sure that everything's
you know statistically steady um so
yeah that was kind of one of the most
important checks to make due to how sort of the
tops the talks in the system establish themselves
uh yeah and checking that's that's all good yeah
yeah so that that's an impressive amount of
time that must have chewed up some series i'm
no hyper diffusion no um which is kind of like
one of the motivations for choosing you know
like stress-free velocity boundary conditions
um just to so we don't have any uh artificial
sort of viscous talks entering the
system sure um okay so then i guess
my other point is is a comment
then really which is you know
you're talking about looking at comparing you
know these fields to um to satellite observations
and so on yeah yeah that's of course only you know
only a single you know time step right yeah yeah
yeah you know decades um and even you know kind
of looking at a decent role you know like gotham
or something still only looking at centuries um so
you know we're not sure quite how representative
that is of the the you know the time average
fields which you're looking at which you know
hundreds of thousands of years potentially
right that you're averaging over
um yeah yeah i'll be encouraging you to to
compare it to the paleomagnetic field as well
and there are these you know these new qpm
criteria um okay which are out there which which
i would i would be very interested to uh run
past these these models and yeah um i would
be wondering um i guess you're the person to ask
like with these paleomagnetic models um is there
enough spatial coverage in order to like sort of
say if i wanted to define this to find this peak
so that would be yeah a good investigation
on its own to see if we've got that
richard bono is probably the best qualified person
in the world to answer that question actually
um for the last few million million
years um i don't know myself um but
i i mean i'm yeah more broadly you know we're
kind of you know we don't have um have full you
know spiral harmonic models but we've been looking
at things like secular variation and the variance
and the in the dipole moment and the inclination
anomaly um so just looking you know that those
are indicating characteristics of the field
okay yeah and say something on whether that
peak and the highlight gp could be spotted or
not yeah it's nice to have like some indications
from the simulations you know just just yeah
it's nice to have them there anyway in case
okay nice to see you again andy
you for your question and thanks uh jenny for
answer them does anybody else has a question
uh oops yes richard susan well susan susan okay
all right i was just wondering if anyone's working
on defining the f layer from the seismology
side are you aware of any ongoing work on that
better yeah yeah yeah because that was kind
of the primary way in which you would uh go
about this and so yeah um i didn't talk about it
much in this presentation because it wasn't um
really the focus but um it was more um yeah
in seismology there are uh i would say pretty
robust observations so like i think closer to
the beginning of my presentation i i talked
about this uh seismically slow key wave that
was observed by syria and pouping a back in 1991
and following that there's been several
independent seismic studies that also see
this slow down in the key wave velocity compared
with prem and prem is the uh reference model
uh it's like a 1d reference model that um is
i don't know uh it's used it's used widely and
i think i said earlier in the presentation that
it assumes that you have an adiabatic profile
so this seismic slowdown in comparison to prem uh
means that you have this infers that you have this
f layer this stably stratified region and um so
a lot of the variants that has been seen in the
seismic um observations is uh the thickness of
the flare which is hard to uh really sort of get
the resolution to to to to get um but this sort
of slowdown is is very very robust so this is
definitely uh uh yeah this is a definite feature
uh that we can see at the base of the article
okay i'll take your word for it it's just 1991 is
quite a lot yeah there are other yeah there are
other studies that um that are like at dow italian
2008 there's also some studies by uh barbara
romanovic as well who's also seen this slow
down um who else uh so yeah there has been other
independent um observations of this slowdown too
okay thank you okay you're welcome thank you uh
thank you again so any other question maybe rachel
you wanted to ask a question yeah oh this is
really interesting jenny thank you um i was just
curious if you had a chance to explore uh magnetic
prandtl numbers and if there's any sensitivity to
the the kind of dynamo behavior with an increasing
uh magnetic yeah um no unfortunately not i think
due to the nature of having quite a short postdoc
it wasn't um within like the scope of what i could
do uh there and then uh like the basic methodology
was to just find a reference good reference model
and then change you know the the two parameters
that i talked about with in regards to their
flare which is the strength of stratification
and the thickness of the f flare it'd be
really interesting to of course vary the
parameters but then it's uh you know it's like
changing my reference case and so um in order to
just really focus on the effects of the f layer
um i've just stuck with this single value but
yeah of course yeah it would be interesting to
see yeah sure great thank you you're welcome
okay thank you anybody else's questions
okay hi hello hello everyone uh yeah
i have a question i was wondering um
do we have any idea about the origin of this uh f
layer how how why why we have where do we have a
yeah yeah um so that was kind of what i tried
to address in my phd work um i don't think i
could go far as far back as to sort of tell
you about the time evolution of the layer but
to actually have an f layer is um is quite
complicated to explain um mainly because
it's very difficult to have a stably
stratified region and also have light
elements pass through this stably stratified
layer because you would think that the
chemical effects from the light elements would
actually stir it up again and you won't have a
stable region anymore so the goal of my phd was to
actually develop a model in which to explain this
which is actually invoking a two-phase system so
um what i developed was a slurry model of the efla
in which you have um iron crystals um
so precipitating out uh which allows
the transport of light elements to pass through
whilst also preserving a stable stratification
so that is one aspect of the question that
i've tried to address but in terms of where
it came from in the whole history of the earth
that's really an open question and so yeah
how it came to be uh would require like more more
researches um i think there has been some sort of
suggestion from my impact modelling like from the
formation of the earth like there could have been
some like thermally stable region in in the
center um but yeah it's not uh that's not
yeah i'm not so familiar with that side of
things though okay thank you thank you guys